<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Folktale>
<!--
    A_11 B_7 depart K_8 M N Ex U w_2   
  -->
 <Move>
 <Preparation>

 In a certain kingdom, in a certain land, there lived a king and a queen, 
 and they had an only daughter, Princess Maria. 
 
 When the queen died, the king took another wife, Yagishna. 
 
 Yagishna gave birth to two daughters: one had two eyes, and the other three eyes. 
 </Preparation>
 <Villainy>
 The stepmother disliked Princess Maria, and ordered her to take Burenushka, 
 the little red cow, to pasture, and gave her a crust of dry bread for her dinner. 
 </Villainy>
 <LiquidationOfLack>
 The princess went to the open field, bowed to Burenushka's right leg, ate and drank her fill, 
 and dressed in fine attire; all day long, dressed like a lady, she tended Burenushka. 
 
 At the end of the day, she again bowed to the little cow's right leg, removed her fine attire, 
 went home carrying back her crust of bread, and put it on the table. 
 </LiquidationOfLack>
 <TaskSolution>
 "How does the slut keep alive?" wondered Yagishna. 
 
 The next day she gave Princess Maria the same crust, and sent her elder daughter with her, saying: 
 
 "Give an eye to what Princess Maria feeds herself with." 
 
 They came to the open field and Princess Maria said: 
 
 "Little sister, let me pick the lice from your head." 
 
 She began to pick them, at the same time saying: 
 
 "Sleep, sleep, little sister! Sleep, sleep, my dear! Sleep, sleep, little eye! Sleep, sleep, other eye!" 
 
 The sister fell asleep, and Princess Maria rose up, went to Burenushka, bowed to her right leg, 
 ate and drank her fill, dressed herself in fine attire, 
 and all day long walked around like a lady. 
 
 Night came; Princess Maria removed her fine attire and said: 
 
 "Get up, little sister, get up, my dear, let us go home." 
 
 "Ah," said the sister unhappily, 
 
 "I have slept through the day, and have not seen anything; now my mother will scold me." 
 
 They came home; the mother asked her: 
 
 "What did Princess Maria eat, what did she drink?" 
 
 "I have not seen anything." 
 
 Yagishna scolded her; 
 
 next morning she got up and sent her three-eyed daughter, saying: 
 
 "Go and see what that slut eats and drinks." 
 
 The girls came to the open field where Burenushka grazed, and Princess Maria said: 
 
 "Little sister, let me pick the lice from your head." 
 
 "Pick them, little sister! Pick them, my dear!" 
 
 Princess Maria began to pick, saying at the same time: 
 
 "Sleep, sleep, little sister! Sleep, sleep, my dear! 
 
 Sleep, sleep, little eye! Sleep, sleep, other eye!" 
 
 She forgot about the third eye, and the third eye looked 
 and looked at what Princess Maria was doing. 

She ran to Burenushka, bowed to her right leg, ate and drank her fill, dressed in fine attire. 

When the sun began to set, she again bowed to Burenushka, removed her fine attire, 
and went to rouse the three-eyed one: 

"Get up, little sister! Get up, my dear! Let us go home!" 

Princess Maria came home and put her dry crust on the table. 

The mother questioned her daughter: 

"What does she eat and drink?" The three-eyed one told everything. 

Yagishna said to her husband: 

"Slaughter Burenushka, old man!" 

And the old man slaughtered the cow. 

Princess Maria begged him: 

"Please, my dear, give me at least a bit of the entrails!" 

The old man threw her a bit of the entrails. 

She took it, placed it on a gatepost, 
and a bush with sweet berries grew up on it, 
and all kinds of little birds perched 
there and sang songs of kings and of peasants. 

Prince Ivan heard about Princess Maria, came to her stepmother, put a dish on the table, and said: 

"Whichever maiden picks a dishful of berries for me, her I will take for my wife." 

Yagishna sent her elder daughter to pick berries; 

the birds did not even let her come near, she had to guard her eyes lest the birds peck them out. 
 
 Yagishna sent her other daughter, and they did not let her come close either. 
 
 At last she sent Princess Maria. 
 
 Princess Maria took the dish and went to pick the berries; 
 
 and as she picked them, the little birds placed twice 
 and thrice as many on the dish as she herself could pick. 
 
 She returned, placed the berries on the table, and bowed to the prince. 
 
 There was a gay feast and a wedding; 
 
 Prince Ivan took Princess Maria away, and they began to live happily and prospered.
 
 After some time, a long time or a short time, Princess Maria gave birth to a son. 
 
 She wanted to visit her father, and went to his house with her husband. 
 
 Her stepmother turned her into a goose and disguised her elder daughter as Prince Ivan's wife. 
 
 Prince Ivan returned home. 
 
 The old tutor of the child got up early in the morning, 
 washed himself very clean, 
 took the baby in his arms, 
 and went to an open field, 
 stopping near a little bush. 
 
 
 Geese came flying, gray geese came. 
 
 "My geese, gray geese! Where have you seen the baby's mother?" "In the next flock." 
 
 The next flock came. 
 
 "My geese, gray geese! Where have you seen the baby's mother?" 
 
 The baby's mother jumped to the ground, tore off her goose skin, 
 took the baby in her arms, and nursed him at her breast, crying: 
 
 "I will nurse him today, 
 I will nurse him tomorrow, 
 but the day after I will fly beyond the forests dark, 
 beyond the mountains high!" 
 
 The old man went home. 
 
 The little fellow slept till next morning without awakening, 
 and the false wife railed at the old man for having gone to the open field 
 and for having starved her son. 
 
 Next morning again he got up very early, 
 washed himself very clean, 
 and went with the child to the open field; 
 
 and Prince Ivan got up, 
 followed the old man unseen, 
 and hid in the bush. 
 
 Geese came flying, gray geese came. 
 
 
 The old man called to them: 
 
 "My geese, gray geese! Where have you seen the baby's mother?" 
 "In the next flock." 
 The next flock came. 
 
 "My geese, gray geese! Where have you seen the baby's mother?" 
 
 The baby's mother jumped to the ground, tore off her goose skin, 
 threw it behind the bush, nursed the baby at her breast, 
 and said farewell to him: 
 
 "Tomorrow I will fly beyond the  forests dark, beyond the mountains high!" 
 
 She gave the baby to the old man and said: 
 
 "Why is there a smell of  burning?" 
 
 She turned to put her goose skin on, and realized that it was gone: Prince Ivan had burned it. 
 
 He grasped Princess Maria; 
 
 she turned into a frog, then into a lizard, 
 and into one kind of loathsome insect after another, 
 and at last into a spindle. 
 
 Prince Ivan broke the spindle in two, threw the top back of him and the bottom in front of him, 
 and a beautiful young woman stood before him. 
 
 They went home together. 
 
 Yagishna's daughter yelled and shouted: "The wrecker is coming, the killer is coming!" 
 
 
 Prince Ivan gathered the dukes and boyars together and asked them: 
 
 "With which wife do you advise me to live?" 
 
 They said: "With the first." 
 
 "Well, gentlemen, whichever wife is the first to climb the gate, with her will I live." 
 
 Yagishna's daughter at once climbed to the top of the gate, but Princess Maria only clutched it 
 and did not climb up. 
 </TaskSolution> 
 <PunishmentOfFalseHero>
 Then Prince Ivan took his gun and shot the false wife, 
 </PunishmentOfFalseHero>
 <Wedding>
 and began to live with Princess 
 Maria as of old, and they prospered. 
 </Wedding>
 <Move>
 <Folktale>
