<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Folktale>
<Move>
<Preparation>
 In A certain kingdom in a certain land there lived a king who had three sons. 
 
 One day they said to him: 
 
 "Father, our gracious sovereign, give us your blessing; 
 
 we wish to go hunting." 
 
 The father gave them his blessing and they set out in different directions. 
 </Preparation>
 <Departure>
 The youngest son rode and rode and lost his way; 
 </Departure>
 <DonorFunctions>
 he came to a clearing, and there lay a dead horse,
 around which were gathered beasts of many kinds, birds, and reptiles. 
 A falcon rose, flew up to the prince, perched on his shoulder, and said: 
 "Prince Ivan, divide that horse among us; 
 it has lain here for thirty years, 
 and we have been quarreling ever since, 
 unable to find a way of sharing it." 
 
 The prince climbed down from his good steed and divided the carcass: 
 he gave the bones to the beasts, 
 the flesh to the birds, 
 the skin to the reptiles, 
 and the head to the ants. 
 
 "Thank you, Prince Ivan," 
 
 said the falcon. 
 
 "For your kindness you shall be able to turn into a bright falcon or an ant whenever you wish." 
 </DonorFunctions>
 
 
 
 <Transfiguration>
 Prince Ivan struck the damp earth, 
 turned into a bright falcon, 
 soared up into the air, 
 and flew to the thrice tenth kingdom. 
 </Transfiguration>
 <Villainy>
 More than half of that kingdom had been swallowed into a crystal mountain. 
 </Villainy>
 
 <ConsentToCounteraction>
 The prince flew straight into the royal palace, 
 turned into a goodly youth, and asked the palace guards: 
 
 "Will your king take me into his service?" 
 "Why should he not take such a goodly youth?" they answered. 
 
 Thus he entered the service of that king and lived in his palace for one week, 
 then a second, 
 then a third. 
 </ConsentToCounteraction>
 <Departure>
 The king's daughter asked her father: 
 "Father, my sovereign, 
 give me leave to take a ride with Prince Ivan to the crystal mountain." 
 
 The king gave her leave. 
 
 They mounted good steeds and set out. 
 </Departure>
 </Move>
 <Move>
 <Villainy>
 When they approached the crystal mountain, 
 a golden goat jumped suddenly out from nowhere. 
 The prince chased it; 
 
 he galloped and galloped, 
 but could not catch the goat, 
 and when he returned the princess had vanished. 
 
 What was he to do? 
 
 How could he dare to appear before the king? 
 </Villainy> <!--Lack -->
 <ConsentToCounterAction>
 He disguised himself as a very old man, 
 so that he would be unrecognizable, 
 came to the palace, 
 and said to the king: 
 
 "Your Majesty, 
 hire me as your herdsman." 
 
 "Very well," 
 said the king, 
 "be my herdsman. 
 
 When the three-headed dragon comes to your herd, 
 give him three cows; 
 
 when the six-headed dragon comes, 
 give him six cows; 
 
 and when the twelve-headed dragon comes, 
 count off twelve cows." 
 </ConsentToCounterAction>
 
  <StruggleVictory>
 Prince Ivan drove his herd over mountains and valleys. 
 Suddenly the three-headed dragon came flying from a lake and said: 
 
 "Ah, Prince Ivan, what kind of work are you engaged in? 
 A goodly youth like you should be vying in combat, 
 not tending cattle. 
 Well, let me have three cows!" 
 
 "Won't that be too much?" asked the prince. 
 
 "I myself eat only one duck a day, 
 and you want three cows. 
 But you won't get any!" 
 
 The dragon flew into a rage, 
 and instead of three cows, 
 seized six. 
 
 Prince Ivan straightway turned into a bright falcon, 
 cut off all the three heads of the dragon, 
 and drove the cattle home. 
 
 "Well, grandfather," 
 asked the king, 
 "has the three-headed dragon come? 
 Did you give him three cows?" 
 "No, Your Majesty," 
 replied Prince Ivan, 
 "I did not give him any." 
  </StruggleVictory>
 
 <StruggleVictory>
 Next day the prince drove his herd over mountains and valleys, 
 and the six-headed dragon came from the lake and demanded six cows. 
 "Ah, you gluttonous monster," 
 said the prince, 
 "I myself eat only one duck a day, 
 and see what you demand! I won't give you any!" 
 The dragon flew into a rage and instead of six, seized twelve cows; 
 but the prince turned into a bright falcon, 
 fell upon the dragon, and cut off his six heads. 
 
 He drove the herd,home and the king asked him: 
 "Well, grandfather, has the six-headed dragon come? 
 Has my herd grown much smaller?" 
 "Come he did, but he took nothing," 
 answered the prince. 
 </StruggleVictory>
 
 <StruggleVictory>
 Late at night Prince Ivan turned into an ant 
  and crawled into the crystal mountain through a little crack. 
 Lo and behold, the princess was in the crystal mountain. 
 "Good evening!" said Prince Ivan. 
 "How did you get here?" 
 "The twelve-headed dragon carried me off," said the princess. 
 "He lives in father's lake and has a coffer in his side. 
 In this coffer is a hare, 
 in this hare is a duck, 
 in this duck is an egg, 
 and in this egg is a seed. 
 
 If you slay the dragon and get that seed, 
 it will be possible to destroy the crystal mountain and rescue me." 
 
 Prince Ivan crawled out of the mountain, 
 turned again into a herdsman, 
 and drove his herd. 
</StruggleVictory>
 <StruggleVictory> 
 Suddenly the twelve-headed dragon flew up to him and said: 
 "Ah, Prince Ivan, 
 you are not doing what you should; 
 a goodly youth like you should be vying in combat, 
 not tending a herd. Well, count off twelve cows for me!" 
 "That will be too much for you!" said the prince. 
 "I myself eat only one duck a day, and see what you demand!" 
 They began to fight, and after a long struggle or a short struggle, 
 Prince Ivan defeated the twelve-headed dragon, 
 slashed open his trunk, and found the coffer in his right side. 
 In the coffer he found a hare, 
 in the hare a duck, 
 in the duck an egg, 
 in the egg a seed. 
 He took the seed, 
 set it alight, 
 and brought it to the crystal mountain, 
 which soon melted away. 
</StruggleVictory>
 <Wedding>
 Prince Ivan led the princess to her father, 
 who was overjoyed and said to the prince: 
 "Be my son-in-law!" 
 The wedding was held at once. 
 </Wedding>
 <Epilogue>
 I was at that wedding too. I drank beer and mead; they flowed down my beard but did not go into my mouth. 
 </Epilogue>
 

</Filler>
<Epilogue>
 
</Epilogue>
</Move>
</Folktale>
