<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Folktale>
<Move>
<Filler>

 In a certain kingdom in a certain land there lived one Bukhtan Bukhtanovich, 
 who had a stove built on pillars in 
 the middle of a field. He lay on the stove on cockroach milk up to his elbows. 
 A fox came to him and said: "
 Bukhtan Bukhtanovich, would you like me to marry you to the tsar's daughter?"

"What's that you're saying, little fox?"

"Do you have any money?"

"I have one five kopek piece."

"Hand it over!" The fox took the coin, exchanged it for smaller coins-- 
kopeks, pennies, and halfpennies, went to 
the tsar, and said: "Tsar give me a quart measure to measure Bukhtan Bukhtanovich's money."

The Tsar said: "Take one!"

The fox took it home, stuck a kopek behind the hoop of the measure, and brought it back to the tsar. 
"Tsar, a 
peck measure is not big enough; give me a bushel measure."

"Take One!"

The fox took it home, stuck what remained of his coins behind the hoop,
and brought it back to the tsar. "Have you measured all his money, little fox?"

The fox answered: "All of it. Now, tsar, I have come for a good purpose: 
give your daughter in marriage to Bukhtan Bukhtanovich."

"Very well; show me the suitor."

The fox ran home. "Bukhtan Bukhtanovich, have you any clothes? Put them on." 

He dressed and , accompanied by the fox, went to the tsar. 

They walked along the market place and had to cross on a board over a muddy ditch. 

The fox gave Bukhtan a push and he fell into the mud. 

The fox ran to him. 

"What is the matter with you, Bukhtan Bukhtanovich?" 

Saying this, the fox smeared him with mud all over. 

"Wait here, Bukhtan Bukhtanovich. 
I shall run to the tsar. 

The fox came to the tsar and said:"Tsar, I was walking with Bukhtan Bukhtanovich on a board over a ditch-- 
it was a wretched little board; we were not careful enough and somehow fell into the mud. 

Bukhtan Bukhtanovich is all dirty and unfit to come to town; have you some clothes to lend him?"

"Here take these"

The fox took the clothes and came to Bukhtan Bukhtanovich. "Here, change your clothes, Bukhtan, and let us go."

They came to the tsar, and at the tar's place the table was already set. Bukhtan did not look at anything except 
himself: He had never seen such clothes in his life. The tsar winked to the fox: "Little fox, why does this 
Bukhtan Bukhtanovich look only at himself?"

"Tsar, I think he is ashamed to be wearing such clothes; never in his life has he worn such mean garments. Tsar, 
give him the garment that you yourself wear on Easter Sunday." and to Bukhtan the fox whispered:"Don't look at 
yourself!"

Bukhtan Bukhtanovich stared at a chair-- it was a gilded one. the tsar again whispered to the fox: "Little fox, 
why does Bukhtan Bukhtanovich look only at that chair?"

"Tsar, in his house such chairs stand only in the bathhouse." The Tzar flung the chair out of the room. The fox 
whispered to Bukhtan: "Do not look at one thing; look here a bit and there a bit."

They began to talk about the purpose of their visit, the match. And then they celebrated the wedding--Does a 
wedding take long in a tsar's palace? there no beer needed to be brewed, no wine distilled--everything is ready. 
Three ships where loaded for Bukhtan Bukhtanovich and they traveled homeward. Bukhtan Bukhtanovich and his wife 
were on one of the ships, and the little fox ran along the shore. Bukhtan saw his stove and cried: "Little fox, 
Little fox, there is my stove."

"Be quiet, Bukhtan Bukhtanovich, that stove is a disgrace."

Bukhtan Bukhtanovich sailed on, and the fox ran ahead of him on the shore. He came to a hill and climbed it. on 
the hill stood a huge stone house, and around it was an enormous kingdom. The fox went into the house and at 
first saw no one; then he ran into a chamber, and there in the best bed lay Dragon, Son of Dragon, stretching 
himself. Raven, Son of Raven, was perched on the chimney, and Cat, Son of Cat, sat on the throne. The fox said: 
"Why are you sitting here? The tsar is coming with fire and the tsarina with lightning, they will scorch and burn
you."

"Little fox, whither shall we go?"

"Cat, Son of Cat, go into the barrel." and the fox sealed him up in the barrel."Raven, Son of Raven, go into 
the mortar!" And the fox sealed him up in the mortar; the he wrapped Dragon, Son of Dragon, in straw and took 
him out into the street.

The ships arrived. The fox ordered all the beasts to be thrown into the water; the cossacks threw them in at once. 
Bukhtan Bukhtanovich moved all of his possessions into that house; there he lived happily and prospered, ruled 
and governed, and there he ended his life.

</Filler>
</Move>
</Folktale>

