<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Folktale>
<Move>
<Filler>
In a certain kingdom, in a country, there lived a king, the king had three sons.
Here children and say to him:
- Dear Sir, sir! Bless us, we'll go on the hunt.

Father has blessed, and they went in different directions.
The younger son went, and went to get lost; leaves a clearing on a glade lies Palaia horse around this fall 
gathered all sorts of animals, birds and reptiles.

Rose falcon, flew to the Tsarevich sat on his shoulder and said:
- Ivan Tsarevich, stripped us this horse, she is thirty-three years here, and we all argue, and how to divide - 
not invent.
Prince dismounted from his horse and shared good carrion beast - bones, birds - meat, leather - reptiles and head - ants.
- Thank you, Ivan Tsarevich! - Said Falcon. - For this service, can you handle a falcon and clear ant whenever 
you want.
Prince Ivan hit the wet ground, became clear falcon soared and flew tridesyatom State, and the State is more than 
half drawn into the crystal mountain.

Flew into the castle, he turned and asked good fellow courtier custody:
- Do not take if your sire me to work for yourself?
- Why do not you take this young man?
Here he went to the king and lives in the service of his week, and another third.
Begged the princess:
- Emperor my father! Let me with Ivan Tsarevich on the crystal mountain walk.
King allowed. They sat on the good horses and drove off.
Approaching the crystal mountain, suddenly, out of nowhere, jumped golden goat.
Prince drove her; rode rode goats not extracted and returned back - and the princess, no! What to do? As king of 
the eye appear?
He dressed such ancient old man that can not recognize; came to the palace and said to the king:
- Your Majesty! Hire me herd graze.
- Well, be a shepherd; fly kite if three heads - give him three cows, if the six heads - give six cows and the 
number of the twelve heads - that is counted twelve cows.
Prince Ivan drove a herd of up hill and down dale, suddenly flies from Lake snakes three heads:
- Ah, Prince Ivan, for what it took you? Where would fight good fellow, and he herd grazes! Well, - he says - I: 
cast three cows.
- Not to be bold? - Meets the prince. - I have to eat sutochki one duck, and you want three cows ... No no you!
The serpent was angry and grabbed six instead of three cows Ivan Tsarevich immediately turned bright falcon, 
rented a three snake head and drove the herd home.
- What, grandfather, - asks the king - a three-headed serpent flew whether, if he gave three cows?
- No, your majesty, no one gave!
The next day the prince drives a herd of up hill and down dale, arrives from the lake about six heads of snakes 
and requires six cows.
- Oh, the miracle Yudo gourmand! I myself eat sutochki one duck, and what you want! I will not give you a single!
The serpent was angry, instead of six captured twelve cows and Prince turned clear falcon, rushed to the snake 
and took him six goals.
Drove home the flock, the king asks:
- What, grandfather, flew six-headed snake if much diminished if my herd?
- Arrives something flew, but did not take anything!
Late in the evening he turned to Ivan Tsarevich and the ant crawled through a small crack in the crystal mountain
, looking - in a crystal mountain sits princess.
- Hello, - says Ivan Tsarevich - how did you get here?
- I took the twelve heads of snakes, he lives on the lake for father. In the snake chest hidden in the trunk - a 
hare in a hare - a duck, a duck - the egg, in the egg - the seed, if you kill him but it get one seed, in those 
days can be a crystal mountain lime and spare me.
Prince Ivan got out of the mountains, shells shepherd and drove a herd.
Suddenly arrives snakes heads of the twelve:
- Ah, Prince Ivan! Not for his cause took you, what would you, good fellows, fight, and you herd pasesh ... Come 
to me shalt twelve cows!
- Fatty will! I myself eat sutochki one duck, and what you want!
Then they began to fight, and long or short it fought - Ivan Tsarevich won twelve of the snake heads, cut his 
torso and on the right side found a chest, the chest - Bunny in a hare - a duck, a duck - egg in an egg - seed .
He took the seed, lit and held it to the crystal mountain - the mountain soon melted.
Prince Ivan brought out the princess and brought her to his father and his father rejoiced and said to Prince:
- If you were my son in law!
</Filler>
<Epilogue>
Here they were married and, at that wedding and I was, honey-beer drinking, beard flowed into the mouth is not 
horrible. 
</Epilogue>
</Move>
</Folktale>
