 
 <?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<Folktale>
<Move>
<Filler>
 Once upon a time there lived a cat, a sparrow, and a brave youth. The cat and the sparrow went to the forest to 
 chop wood and said to the brave youth: "You keep the house, but mind you: if Baba Yaga comes and counts the 
 spoons, do not say a word, keep quiet!" "Very well," said the brave youth. The cat and the sparrow went away, 
 and the brave youth sat on the stove behind the chimney. Suddenly Baba Yaga came in, took the spoons, and began  to count them: "This is the cat's spoon, this is the sparrow's spoon, and this is 
 
 the brave youth's spoon." The brave youth could not restrain himself and cried: "Baba Yaga, don't touch my 
 spoon!" Baba Yaga seized the brave youth, sat on the mortar, and flew off; she drove the mortar, spurring it 
 with the pestle and sweeping away her tracks with her broom. The brave youth shouted: "Cat, run! Sparrow, fly!" 
 They heard him and rushed to his help. The cat began to scratch Baba Yaga and the sparrow to peck at her; thus   they rescued the brave youth. 
 The next day the cat and the sparrow again prepared to go to the forest to chop wood, and told the brave youth:  
 "Mind you, if Baba Yaga comes, do not say anything; today we are going far away." As soon as the brave youth had 
 sat down on the stove behind the chimney, Baba Yaga came again, and again began to count the spoons: "This is  
 the cat's spoon, this is the sparrow's spoon, and this is the brave youth's spoon." The brave youth could not 
 restrain himself and shouted: "Baba Yaga, don't touch my spoon!" Baba Yaga seized the brave youth and dragged 
 him along with her. The brave youth shouted: "Cat, run! Sparrow, fly!" They heard him and rushed to his help. 
 The cat began to scratch and the sparrow to peck at Baba Yaga. Thus they rescued the brave youth. Then they all 
 went home. 
 The third day the cat and the sparrow prepared once more to go to the forest and chop wood, and they said to the 
 brave youth: "Mind you, if Baba Yaga comes, be silent; today we are going even farther." 
 The cat and the sparrow 
 left, and the brave youth sat on the stove behind the chimney. Suddenly Baba Yaga again took the spoons and 
 began to count them: "This is the cat's spoon, this is the sparrow's spoon, this is the brave youth's spoon." 
 The brave youth did not say a word. Baba Yaga counted again: "This is the cat's spoon, this is the sparrow's 
 spoon, and this is the brave youth's spoon." The brave youth did not say a word. Baba Yaga counted a third time: 
 "This is the cat's spoon, this is the sparrow's spoon, and this is the brave youth's spoon." The brave youth 
 could not restrain himself any longer and cried loudly: "Don't touch my spoon!" Baba Yaga seized the brave youth 
 and dragged him along with her. He cried: "Cat, run! Sparrow, fly!" But his 
 
 brothers did not hear him. Baba Yaga took him home, put him in the wooden shed by the stove, made a fire in the 
 stove, and said to her eldest daughter: "I am going to Russia. Meanwhile, roast this brave youth for my dinner." 
 "Very well," said the daughter. 
 The stove grew hot and the girl told the brave youth to come out of the shed. He came out. "Lie down on the 
 roasting pan," said the girl. He lay down, held up one of his feet so that it touched the ceiling, and put the 
 other on the floor. The girl said: "Not that way, not that way!" The brave youth said: "How then? Show me." The 
 girl lay down on the roasting pan. The brave youth quickly seized an oven fork, pushed the pan with Baba Yaga's 
 daughter on it into the oven, and went back into the shed to wait for Baba Yaga. Suddenly she ran in and said: 
 "Now I am going to feast and regale myself on the brave youth's bones!" The brave youth answered her: "Feast and 
 regale yourself on your own daughter's bones!" Baba Yaga was startled and looked into the oven. She found her 
 daughter all roasted, and roared: "Aha, you cheat, just wait, you won't get away!" She ordered her second 
 daughter to roast the brave youth and went away. 
 Her second daughter made a fire in the stove and told the brave youth to come out. He came out, lay on the pan, 
 put one foot on the ceiling and the other on the floor. 
 
 The girl said: "Not that way, not that way!" "Show me how." 
 
 The girl lay on the pan. The brave youth shoved her into the oven, went back to the shed, and sat there. 
 Suddenly he heard Baba Yaga crying: "Now I am going to feast and regale myself on the brave youth's bones!" He 
 answered: "Feast and regale yourself on your own daughter's bones!" Baba Yaga flew into a rage: "Eh," she said, 
 "just wait, you won't get away!" 
 She ordered her youngest daughter to roast him, but to no avail; the brave youth shoved her into the oven too. 
 Baba Yaga flew into an even greater rage: "Now," she said, "this time I swear you won't get away!" She made a 
 fire in the stove and cried: "Come out, brave youth, lie on the pan!" He lay down, touched the ceiling with one 
 foot, the floor with the other, and thus could not be got into the oven. Baba Yaga said: "Not that 
 
 way, not that way!" And the brave youth still pretended that he did not know how. "I don't know how," he said. 
 "Show me." Baba Yaga at once curled up and lay on the pan. The brave youth quickly shoved her into the oven, ran 
 home, and said to his brothers: "That's what I did with Baba Yaga!" 

</Filler>
</Move>
</Folktale>
