<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Folktale>
<Move>
<Filler>
In some kingdom, in some state there lived-was the tsar; 
at this tsar was three daughters and one son, Ivan-tsarevitch. 
The tsar has grown old and has died, and the crown was accepted by Ivan-tsarevitch.
      As the next kings have learnt about that, have now collected incalculable armies and have gone on it войною. 
      Ivan
      -tsarevitch does not know, how to it to be; comes to sisters and asks:
      - Kind my sisters! What to me to do? All kings have risen on me войною.
      - Ah you, the brave soldier! Of that was frightened? How White Полянин is at war with the woman-jagoju - 
      gold 
      ногою, thirty years from a horse does not climb down, роздыху does not know? And you, nothing seeing, were 
      frightened!
      Ivan-tsarevitch has immediately saddled the kind horse, has put on a harness military, took a sword-kladenets
      , a 
      spear долгомерное and плетку silk and has left against the enemy. 
      The falcon is not clear flies on herd of geese, 
      swans and on grey утиц - Ivan-tsarevitch attacks an army вражее; 
      not so much sword beats, how many a horse 
      tramples down; has interrupted all troops вражее, it was turned back in a city, has laid down to sleep and 
      slept 
      three days a deep dream. - for the fourth days has woken up, left on a balcony, has looked in an open country 
      - 
      kings more than that armies have collected and again under the walls have risen.
      Запечалился a tsarevitch, goes to sisters:
      - Ah, sisters! What to me to do? One force has exterminated, another under a city costs, more threatens.
      - What you the soldier! Days was at war yes three days without просыпа slept. How White Полянин is at war 
      with the 
      
      woman-jagoju - gold ногою, thirty years from a horse does not climb down, роздыху does not know?
      Ivan-tsarevitch has run in белокаменные stables, has saddled a kind horse powerful, has put on a harness 
      military, 
      has surrounded a sword-kladenets, in one hand took a spear долгомерное, in another - 
      плетку silk and has left against the enemy.
      The falcon is not clear flies on herd of geese, swans and on grey утиц - 
      Ivan-tsarevitch attacks an army вражее; 
      not so much itself beats, how many the horse tramples down it. Has beaten a host-force great, 
      it was turned back 
      home, has laid down to sleep and was fast asleep six days.
      For the seventh days has woken up, left on a balcony,
      has looked in an open country kings more than that armies 
      have collected and again all city have surrounded.
      There is Ivan-tsarevitch to sisters:
      - Kind my sisters! What to me to do? Two forces has exterminated, the third under walls costs, still more 
      threatens.
      - Ah you, the brave soldier! One days was at war yes six without просыпа slept. 
      How White Полянин is at war with 
      the woman-jagoju - gold ногою, thirty years from a horse does not climb down, роздыху does not know?
      Bitterly that seemed to a tsarevitch; he has run in белокаменные stables, 
      has saddled the kind horse powerful, has 
      put on a harness military, has surrounded a sword-kladenets, in one hand took a spear долгомерное, 
      in another - 
      плетку silk and has left against the enemy.
      The falcon is not clear flies on herd of geese, swans and on grey утиц - 
      Ivan-tsarevitch attacks an army вражее; 
      not so much itself beats, how many the horse tramples down it. Has beaten a host-force great, 
      it was turned back 
      home, has laid down to sleep and was fast asleep nine days.
      For the tenth days has woken up, has called all ministers and senators:
      - Misters my ministers and senators! I have taken in head to go to another's countries,
      on White Полянина to look;
      </Filler>
      </Move>
</Folktale>
