<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Corpus>


<!--
 A_9 B_5 D1_1 E1_1 F1_1 return MOVE
   a_6 B_5 C depart D1_1 E1_1 F1 return -->
<Folktale>
<Move>
<Preparation>
There was once a stepmother who had a stepdaughter and a daughter of her own.
 At anything her own daughter did, the woman would pat her head and say:
 "Clever girl!" But no matter how hard the stepdaughter tried, she was always found in the wrong.
 Yet the truth of the matter was that the stepdaughter was as good as gold;
 in the proper hands she would have been like cheese in butter, but in her stepmother's house
 she bathed in tears every day. What could she do? Even an angry wind subsides at last;
 but when the old woman got angry she never quieted down, she would hurl one insult after another,
 and her mouth was so full of venom that her teeth itched.

 One day the stepmother made up her mind to drive her stepdaughter out of the house.
 She said to her husband:
 "Take her, take her, old man, take her wherever you wish,
 so that my eyes do not see her and my ears do not hear her.
 And don't take her to the warm house of your kin,
 but into the open field in the bitter frost."

 </Preparation>
<Villainy> 

 The old man began to grieve and lament; 
 none the less he put his daughter on a sledge.
 
 He wanted to cover her with a horse cloth but did not dare.
 
 He took the homeless girl into the open field, set her down on a heap of snow,
 made the sign of the cross over her, and hastened home as fast as possible,
 that his eyes might not behold his daughter's death. </Villainy>
 
 <DonorFunctions>
 The poor little thing remained there shivering and softly repeating her prayers.
 
 Jack Frost came leaping and jumping and casting glances at the lovely maiden.
 
 "Maiden, maiden, I am Jack Frost the Ruby-nosed!" he said.
 "Welcome, Jack Frost! God must have sent you to save my sinful soul."
 
 Jack Frost was about to crack her body and freeze her to death,
 but he was touched by her wise words, pitied her, and tossed her a fur coat.
 
 She put it on, squatted on her heels, and sat thus.
 Again Jack Frost the Ruby-nosed came leaping and jumping and casting glances at the lovely maiden.
 
 "Maiden, maiden, I am Jack Frost the Ruby-nosed!" he said.
 
 "Welcome, Jack Frost! God must have sent you to save my sinful soul."
 But Jack Frost had not come to save her soul at all;
 
 he brought her a coffer, deep and heavy, 
 full of bedding and petticoats and all sorts of things for her dowry.
 
 And she sat on the coffer in her fur coat, so gay, so pretty!
 Again Jack Frost came leaping and jumping and casting glances at the lovely maiden.
 She welcomed him and he gave her a robe embroidered with silver and gold.
 She put it on-and how beautiful and stately she looked!
 She sat there happily singing songs.
 </DonorFunctions>
 <Return>
 Meanwhile her stepmother was preparing her funeral dinner and frying pancakes.
 "Go, husband," she said, "bring home your daughter, that we may bury her."
 The old man went. The little dog under the table said:
 "Bow-wow, the old man's daughter is coming home all decked in gold and silver,
 but no suitor wants the old woman's daughter!"
 
 
 "Be quiet, you fool! Here is a pancake for you,
 and now say that suitors will come for the old woman's daughter,
 but of the old man's daughter only bones will be brought home."
 
 The little dog ate the pancake and said again:
 "Bow-wow! The old man's daughter is coming home all decked in gold and silver,
 but the suitors don't want the old woman's daughter."
 
 The old woman gave the dog more pancakes and beat him,
 but he kept saying the same thing:
 "The old man's daughter is coming home decked in gold and silver,
 but the suitors don't want the old woman's daughter."
 
 The gate creaked, the doors flew wide open,
 a coffer deep and heavy was brought in,
 and the stepdaughter followed, radiant, like a grand lady.
 </Return>
 </Move>
<Move>
<Villainy>
 The stepmother looked at her and threw up her arms.
 
 "Old man, old man," she ordered, "harness other horses, take my daughter at once,
 put her in the same field, in the very same place!"
 </Villainy>
<Departure>
 The old man took the girl to the same field and left her in the very same place.
 </Departure>
<DonorFunctions>
 And Jack Frost the Ruby-nosed came, looked at his guest, leapt and jumped,
 but did not hear any kind words. 
 
 He grew angry, seized her, and killed her.
</DonorFunctions>
<AlienForms> 
 The old woman said to her husband:
 "Old man, go bring my daughter.
 Harness spirited horses-and don't overturn the sledge, don't drop the coffer!"
 
 But the little dog under the table said:
 "Bow-wow, the suitors will take the old man's daughter,
 but the bones of the old woman's daughter will be brought home in a sack."
 
 "Don't lie! here is a pancake for you, and say:
 'The old woman's daughter is coming home decked in gold and silver.'
 
 "The gate flew open and the old woman ran out to greet her daughter,
 but instead she embraced a cold corpse. She began to wail and howl, but it was too late.
</AlienForms>
</Move>
</Folktale>
 


<!--
 A_9 B_5 D1_1 E1_1 F1_1 return MOVE
   a_6 B_5 C depart D1_1 E1_1 F1 return -->
<Folktale>
<Move>
<Preparation>
There was once a stepmother who had a stepdaughter and a daughter of her own.
 At anything her own daughter did, the woman would pat her head and say:
 "Clever girl!" But no matter how hard the stepdaughter tried, she was always found in the wrong.
 Yet the truth of the matter was that the stepdaughter was as good as gold;
 in the proper hands she would have been like cheese in butter, but in her stepmother's house
 she bathed in tears every day. What could she do? Even an angry wind subsides at last;
 but when the old woman got angry she never quieted down, she would hurl one insult after another,
 and her mouth was so full of venom that her teeth itched.

 One day the stepmother made up her mind to drive her stepdaughter out of the house.
 She said to her husband:
 "Take her, take her, old man, take her wherever you wish,
 so that my eyes do not see her and my ears do not hear her.
 And don't take her to the warm house of your kin,
 but into the open field in the bitter frost."

 </Preparation>
<Villainy> 

 The old man began to grieve and lament; 
 none the less he put his daughter on a sledge.
 
 He wanted to cover her with a horse cloth but did not dare.
 
 He took the homeless girl into the open field, set her down on a heap of snow,
 made the sign of the cross over her, and hastened home as fast as possible,
 that his eyes might not behold his daughter's death. </Villainy>
 
 <DonorFunctions>
 The poor little thing remained there shivering and softly repeating her prayers.
 
 Jack Frost came leaping and jumping and casting glances at the lovely maiden.
 
 "Maiden, maiden, I am Jack Frost the Ruby-nosed!" he said.
 "Welcome, Jack Frost! God must have sent you to save my sinful soul."
 
 Jack Frost was about to crack her body and freeze her to death,
 but he was touched by her wise words, pitied her, and tossed her a fur coat.
 
 She put it on, squatted on her heels, and sat thus.
 Again Jack Frost the Ruby-nosed came leaping and jumping and casting glances at the lovely maiden.
 
 "Maiden, maiden, I am Jack Frost the Ruby-nosed!" he said.
 
 "Welcome, Jack Frost! God must have sent you to save my sinful soul."
 But Jack Frost had not come to save her soul at all;
 
 he brought her a coffer, deep and heavy, 
 full of bedding and petticoats and all sorts of things for her dowry.
 
 And she sat on the coffer in her fur coat, so gay, so pretty!
 Again Jack Frost came leaping and jumping and casting glances at the lovely maiden.
 She welcomed him and he gave her a robe embroidered with silver and gold.
 She put it on-and how beautiful and stately she looked!
 She sat there happily singing songs.
 </DonorFunctions>
 <Return>
 Meanwhile her stepmother was preparing her funeral dinner and frying pancakes.
 "Go, husband," she said, "bring home your daughter, that we may bury her."
 The old man went. The little dog under the table said:
 "Bow-wow, the old man's daughter is coming home all decked in gold and silver,
 but no suitor wants the old woman's daughter!"
 
 
 "Be quiet, you fool! Here is a pancake for you,
 and now say that suitors will come for the old woman's daughter,
 but of the old man's daughter only bones will be brought home."
 
 The little dog ate the pancake and said again:
 "Bow-wow! The old man's daughter is coming home all decked in gold and silver,
 but the suitors don't want the old woman's daughter."
 
 The old woman gave the dog more pancakes and beat him,
 but he kept saying the same thing:
 "The old man's daughter is coming home decked in gold and silver,
 but the suitors don't want the old woman's daughter."
 
 The gate creaked, the doors flew wide open,
 a coffer deep and heavy was brought in,
 and the stepdaughter followed, radiant, like a grand lady.
 </Return>
</Move>
<Move>
 <Villainy>
 The stepmother looked at her and threw up her arms.
 
 "Old man, old man," she ordered, "harness other horses, take my daughter at once,
 put her in the same field, in the very same place!"
 </Villainy>
<Departure>
 The old man took the girl to the same field and left her in the very same place.
 </Departure>
<DonorFunctions>
 And Jack Frost the Ruby-nosed came, looked at his guest, leapt and jumped,
 but did not hear any kind words. 
 
 He grew angry, seized her, and killed her.
</DonorFunctions>
<AlienForms> 
 The old woman said to her husband:
 "Old man, go bring my daughter.
 Harness spirited horses-and don't overturn the sledge, don't drop the coffer!"
 
 But the little dog under the table said:
 "Bow-wow, the suitors will take the old man's daughter,
 but the bones of the old woman's daughter will be brought home in a sack."
 
 "Don't lie! here is a pancake for you, and say:
 'The old woman's daughter is coming home decked in gold and silver.'
 
 "The gate flew open and the old woman ran out to greet her daughter,
 but instead she embraced a cold corpse. She began to wail and howl, but it was too late.
</AlienForms>
</Move>
</Folktale>
 



<Folktale>
<!-- Propp says: 
 AFAN98 -->
<Move>
<Preparation>
 Night and day a certain old stepmother grumbled-one wondered why her tongue did not ache!
 
 She grumbled always at her stepdaughter:
 
 the girl was not clever enough and not pretty enough; no matter where she went or sat or stood,
 it was never right,
 never as it should be!
 </Preparation>
 
 <Villainy>
 And so the stepmother grumbled from dawn to dark like a gusla all wound up.
 
 She wearied her husband to death, and everyone else too felt like running away from the house.
 
 One day the husband harnessed a horse to carry millet to town,
 
 and his wife cried:
 
 "Take your daughter too, take her anywhere you want, to the dark forest, only get her out of my way!"
 </Villainy>
 
 <Departure>
 The old man took his daughter.
 
 It was a long and difficult road, with woods and swamps all around;
 
 where could he leave the maiden? He spied a little hut on chicken legs,
 supported by a cake and covered with a pancake; and the little hut turned round and round.
 </Departure>
 <ConnectiveIncident>
 He thought it would be best to leave his daughter in this little hut;
 
 so he put her down from his cart, gave her some millet for gruel, whipped his horse, and vanished from sight.
 
 The maiden remained alone;
 
 she pounded some millet and cooked a great deal of gruel, but there was no one to eat it.
 
 Night came, long and terrifying;
 
 she felt that to sleep would wear out her sides,
 to look at the dark would tire her eyes,
 and there was no one to exchange a word with.
 
 </ConnectiveIncident>
 
 <DonorFunctions>
 It was boring and fearsome.
 
 She stood on the threshold, opened the door nearest the forest, and called out:
 
 "Whoever is in the forest, in the dark night, let him come be my guest!"
 
 
 A wood goblin answered her call and turned into a brave youth, a Novgorod merchant;
 
 
 
 he came into the little hut and brought a present for his hostess.
 
 
 
 After that he came in for a chat quite often and sometimes he would bring her a gift;
 
 
 he brought her so many gifts that there was no place to put them.
 
 
 
 
 
 Meanwhile the grumbling old woman found life empty without her stepdaughter;
 
 it was quiet in her house, she felt queasy, and her tongue was parched.
 
 "Go, husband," she said,
 
 "get my stepdaughter, raise her up from the bottom of the sea, snatch her out of the fire!
 
 I am old, I am sickly, there is no one to tend me."
 
 </DonorFunctions>
 <Return>
 
 The husband did as she asked;
 
 the stepdaughter returned.
 </Return>
 <AlienForms>
 When she opened her coffer and hung out her things on a rope that stretched from the house to the gate,
 
 the old woman, who had opened her mouth to greet her in her customary abusive way, pursed up her lips,
 
 seated the welcome guest under the icon, and said to her civilly:
 
 "What is your pleasure, madam?"

</AlienForms>
</Move>
 
</Folktale>




<Folktale>
<!-- Propp says: 
 I:  A9 B5 D1 E1 f1 Return Departure
 II: a6 D1 Departure B2_5 E-F = Return
-->
<Move>
<Preparation>
 A widowed peasant with a daughter married a widow who also had a daughter; 
 
 thus they each had a stepchild. 
</Preparation>
<Villainy>
 The stepmother was envious and nagged the old man constantly, saying: 
 
 "Take your daughter to the woods, to a mud hut; there she will spin more." 
 
 What could the peasant do? 
 
 He did as his wife told him, took his daughter to a mud hut, 
 gave her a steel and flint and a bag of grits, and said: 
 
 "Here is fire for you, do not let it die out; cook your kasha, sit and spin, and keep the hut locked." 
 </Villainy>
 <DonorFunctions>
 Night came. 
 
 The girl heated the stove and cooked her kasha; 
 
 from somewhere a little mouse came out and said: "Maiden, maiden, give me a spoonful of kasha." 
 "Oh, little mouse, cheer me in my loneliness, 
 and I will give you more than one spoonful of kasha. 
 I shall let you eat your fill of it." 
 
 The mouse ate his fill and left. 
 At night a bear broke into the hut and said: 
 
 "Now, girl, put out the light and let us play blindman's buff." 
 The mouse ran up the maiden's shoulder and whispered into her ear: 
 "Fear not, maiden. Say to him, 'Very well, let us play.' 
 Then put out the light and crawl under the stove; I shall run about and ring the little bell." 
 So they did. 
 The bear chased the little mouse but could not catch him; 
 he began to roar and hurl logs of wood; 
 he hurled and hurled them but did not hit his mark.
 He got tired and said: "Ah, little girl, you're an expert player of blindman's buff. 
 </DonorFunctions>
 <Filler>
 
 To reward you I shall send you a drove of horses and a cartful of goods tomorrow morning." 
 Next morning the old man's wife said: 
 "Go, old man, visit your daughter, see how much she has spun since yesterday." 
 </Filler>
 <Return>
 
 The old man went and his wife sat and waited for him to bring back his daughter's bones. 
 Suddenly the dog began to bark: 
 "Bow-wow-wow, the daughter is coming, 
 with her father driving a drove of horses and bringing a cartful of goods." 
 
 "You're lying, dog! Those are her bones rattling and clattering in my husband's basket." 
  </Return>
 </Move>
 
 <Move>
 <Lack>
 The gate creaked, the horses ran into the yard, 
 and the stepmother beheld the father and daughter sitting on a cart laden with goods. 


  The woman's eyes gleamed with greed. 
 "That's not very much," she cried. "Now take my daughter to the woods for the night. 
 
 She will come home driving two droves of horses and bringing two cartfuls of goods." 
 </Lack>
 <DonorFunctions>
 The peasant took his wife's daughter to the mud hut and provided her also with food and fire. 
 At nightfall she cooked gruel. 
 
 The mouse came and asked her for some kasha. 
 
 But she cried: "Oh, you vermin!" And she hurled a spoon at him. 
 
 The mouse ran away, Natasha gobbled up all the kasha by herself, 
 and, having eaten, put out the light and lay down in a corner. 
 At midnight the bear broke into the mud hut and said: 
 
 "Hey, where are you, little girl? Let's play blindman's buff." 
 
 The maiden did not answer, but her teeth rattled from fear. 
 
 "Ah, so there you are! Here's a little bell. Run, I will try to catch you." 
 She took the little bell, her hand trembled, the bell rang incessantly, and the mouse said: 
 "That wicked maiden will meet her death." 
 </DonorFunctions>
 <Return>
 Next morning the wife sent the old man to the woods, saying: 
 "Go now! My daughter will bring back two cartfuls of goods and drive two droves of horses." 
 The peasant went and his wife sat at the gate. 
 
 The dog barked: 
 "Bow-wow-wow, the wife's daughter is coming, her bones are rattling in the basket, 
 and the old man sits on an empty cart." 
 
 "You're lying, dog! My daughter is driving herds and bringing full carts." 
 
 She looked up and there was the old man at the gate. 
 
 He handed his wife a basket; she opened the basket, saw the bones, began to howl, 
 and grew so angry that from grief and spite she died the next day. 
 </Return>
 <Wedding>
 But the old man lived happily with his daughter all his life 
 and took into his house a wealthy son-in-law. 
 </Wedding>
</Move>
</Folktale>







<Folktale>
<!--
    A_11 B_7 depart K_8 M N Ex U w_2   
  -->
 <Move>
 <Preparation>

 In A certain kingdom, in a certain land, there lived a king and a queen, 
 and they had an only daughter, Princess Maria. 
 
 When the queen died, the king took another wife, Yagishna. 
 
 Yagishna gave birth to two daughters: one had two eyes, and the other three eyes. 
 </Preparation>
 <Villainy>
 The stepmother disliked Princess Maria, and ordered her to take Burenushka, 
 the little red cow, to pasture, and gave her a crust of dry bread for her dinner. 
 </Villainy>
 <LiquidationOfLack>
 The princess went to the open field, bowed to Burenushka's right leg, ate and drank her fill, 
 and dressed in fine attire; all day long, dressed like a lady, she tended Burenushka. 
 
 At the end of the day, she again bowed to the little cow's right leg, removed her fine attire, 
 went home carrying back her crust of bread, and put it on the table. 
 </LiquidationOfLack>
 <TaskSolution>
 "How does the slut keep alive?" wondered Yagishna. 
 
 The next day she gave Princess Maria the same crust, and sent her elder daughter with her, saying: 
 
 "Give an eye to what Princess Maria feeds herself with." 
 
 They came to the open field and Princess Maria said: 
 
 "Little sister, let me pick the lice from your head." 
 
 She began to pick them, at the same time saying: 
 
 "Sleep, sleep, little sister! Sleep, sleep, my dear! Sleep, sleep, little eye! Sleep, sleep, other eye!" 
 
 The sister fell asleep, and Princess Maria rose up, went to Burenushka, bowed to her right leg, 
 ate and drank her fill, dressed herself in fine attire, 
 and all day long walked around like a lady. 
 
 Night came; Princess Maria removed her fine attire and said: 
 
 "Get up, little sister, get up, my dear, let us go home." 
 
 "Ah," said the sister unhappily, 
 
 "I have slept through the day, and have not seen anything; now my mother will scold me." 
 
 They came home; the mother asked her: 
 
 "What did Princess Maria eat, what did she drink?" 
 
 "I have not seen anything." 
 
 Yagishna scolded her; 
 
 next morning she got up and sent her three-eyed daughter, saying: 
 
 "Go and see what that slut eats and drinks." 
 
 The girls came to the open field where Burenushka grazed, and Princess Maria said: 
 
 "Little sister, let me pick the lice from your head." 
 
 "Pick them, little sister! Pick them, my dear!" 
 
 Princess Maria began to pick, saying at the same time: 
 
 "Sleep, sleep, little sister! Sleep, sleep, my dear! 
 
 Sleep, sleep, little eye! Sleep, sleep, other eye!" 
 
 She forgot about the third eye, and the third eye looked 
 and looked at what Princess Maria was doing. 

She ran to Burenushka, bowed to her right leg, ate and drank her fill, dressed in fine attire. 

When the sun began to set, she again bowed to Burenushka, removed her fine attire, 
and went to rouse the three-eyed one: 

"Get up, little sister! Get up, my dear! Let us go home!" 

Princess Maria came home and put her dry crust on the table. 

The mother questioned her daughter: 

"What does she eat and drink?" The three-eyed one told everything. 

Yagishna said to her husband: 

"Slaughter Burenushka, old man!" 

And the old man slaughtered the cow. 

Princess Maria begged him: 

"Please, my dear, give me at least a bit of the entrails!" 

The old man threw her a bit of the entrails. 

She took it, placed it on a gatepost, 
and a bush with sweet berries grew up on it, 
and all kinds of little birds perched 
there and sang songs of kings and of peasants. 

Prince Ivan heard about Princess Maria, came to her stepmother, put a dish on the table, and said: 

"Whichever maiden picks a dishful of berries for me, her I will take for my wife." 

Yagishna sent her elder daughter to pick berries; 

the birds did not even let her come near, she had to guard her eyes lest the birds peck them out. 
 
 Yagishna sent her other daughter, and they did not let her come close either. 
 
 At last she sent Princess Maria. 
 
 Princess Maria took the dish and went to pick the berries; 
 
 and as she picked them, the little birds placed twice 
 and thrice as many on the dish as she herself could pick. 
 
 She returned, placed the berries on the table, and bowed to the prince. 
 
 There was a gay feast and a wedding; 
 
 Prince Ivan took Princess Maria away, and they began to live happily and prospered.
 
 After some time, a long time or a short time, Princess Maria gave birth to a son. 
 
 She wanted to visit her father, and went to his house with her husband. 
 
 Her stepmother turned her into a goose and disguised her elder daughter as Prince Ivan's wife. 
 
 Prince Ivan returned home. 
 
 The old tutor of the child got up early in the morning, 
 washed himself very clean, 
 took the baby in his arms, 
 and went to an open field, 
 stopping near a little bush. 
 
 
 Geese came flying, gray geese came. 
 
 "My geese, gray geese! Where have you seen the baby's mother?" "In the next flock." 
 
 The next flock came. 
 
 "My geese, gray geese! Where have you seen the baby's mother?" 
 
 The baby's mother jumped to the ground, tore off her goose skin, 
 took the baby in her arms, and nursed him at her breast, crying: 
 
 "I will nurse him today, 
 I will nurse him tomorrow, 
 but the day after I will fly beyond the forests dark, 
 beyond the mountains high!" 
 
 The old man went home. 
 
 The little fellow slept till next morning without awakening, 
 and the false wife railed at the old man for having gone to the open field 
 and for having starved her son. 
 
 Next morning again he got up very early, 
 washed himself very clean, 
 and went with the child to the open field; 
 
 and Prince Ivan got up, 
 followed the old man unseen, 
 and hid in the bush. 
 
 Geese came flying, gray geese came. 
 
 
 The old man called to them: 
 
 "My geese, gray geese! Where have you seen the baby's mother?" 
 "In the next flock." 
 The next flock came. 
 
 "My geese, gray geese! Where have you seen the baby's mother?" 
 
 The baby's mother jumped to the ground, tore off her goose skin, 
 threw it behind the bush, nursed the baby at her breast, 
 and said farewell to him: 
 
 "Tomorrow I will fly beyond the  forests dark, beyond the mountains high!" 
 
 She gave the baby to the old man and said: 
 
 "Why is there a smell of  burning?" 
 
 She turned to put her goose skin on, and realized that it was gone: Prince Ivan had burned it. 
 
 He grasped Princess Maria; 
 
 she turned into a frog, then into a lizard, 
 and into one kind of loathsome insect after another, 
 and at last into a spindle. 
 
 Prince Ivan broke the spindle in two, threw the top back of him and the bottom in front of him, 
 and a beautiful young woman stood before him. 
 
 They went home together. 
 
 Yagishna's daughter yelled and shouted: "The wrecker is coming, the killer is coming!" 
 
 
 Prince Ivan gathered the dukes and boyars together and asked them: 
 
 "With which wife do you advise me to live?" 
 
 They said: "With the first." 
 
 "Well, gentlemen, whichever wife is the first to climb the gate, with her will I live." 
 
 Yagishna's daughter at once climbed to the top of the gate, but Princess Maria only clutched it 
 and did not climb up. 
 </TaskSolution> 
 <PunishmentOfFalseHero>
 Then Prince Ivan took his gun and shot the false wife, 
 </PunishmentOfFalseHero>
 <Wedding>
 and began to live with Princess 
 Maria as of old, and they prospered. 
 </Wedding>
 </Move>
 </Folktale>






 
 

<Folktale>
<!-- Propp says: two moves same as 95 (PG. 145 of the _Morphology_):
     I:  B5 D1 E1 A9 f1 Return
     II: a6 B2-5 C D1 Departure E.neg. 1 F = Return -->

<Move>
 <Preparation>
 Once upon A time there lived an old man and his wife. 
 When the old man became a widower, 
 he married another wife, 
 although he had a daughter from his first wife. 
 </Preparation>
 <Villainy>
 The wicked stepmother disliked the girl, beat her, and pondered how she might destroy her. 
 
 One day the father went away somewhere and the stepmother said to the girl: 
 "Go to your aunt, my sister; 
 ask her for a needle and some thread to sew a shirt for you." 
 </Villainy>
 
 <ConnectiveIncident>
 That aunt was Baba Yaga the Bony-legged. The girl was not stupid and she first went to her own aunt. 
 "Good day, auntie," she said. 
 "Good day, my beloved, what have you come for?" said her aunt. 
 
 "Mother has sent me to her sister to ask for a needle and thread to sew me a shirt." 
 </ConnectiveIncident>
 <DonorFunctions>
 The aunt told her what to do. "My little niece," she said,
 "when you get there, a birch will lash your eyes, but do you tie it with a ribbon. 
 
 The gates will bang and creak at you, but do you pour some oil on their hinges. 
 Dogs will want to tear you apart, but do you throw them some bread. 
 A cat will scratch your eyes, but do you give him some ham." 

 
 The girl went her way; 
 she walked and walked and finally arrived at her other aunt's. 
 
 She saw a little hut and in it sat Baha Yaga the Bony-legged. 
 
 "Good day, auntie," said the girl. 
 
 "Good day, my beloved!" 
 
 "Mother sent me to ask for a needle and thread to sew me a shirt." 
 
 "Very well; meanwhile sit down and weave." 
 
 The girl sat at the loom and Baba Yaga went out and said to her maid: 
 
 "Go and heat a bath and wash my niece, but be careful; 
 I want to eat her for breakfast." 
 
 The girl sat there half dead with fright and begged the maid: 
 
 "My dear, do not burn so much wood! 
 Pour water over it and bring the water in a sieve." 
 
 And she gave the maid a kerchief. 
 
 Baba Yaga waited. 
 
 She came to the window and asked: 
 
 "Are you weaving, little niece, are you weaving, my darling?" 
 
 "I am weaving, auntie, I am weaving, my dear." 
 
 Baba Yaga went away from the window and the girl gave ham to the cat and asked him: 
 
 "Is there no way of getting away from here?" 
 "Here is a comb and a towel," said the cat. 
 
 "Take them and run away. 
 
 Baba Yaga will pursue you. 
 
 But do you put your ear to the ground, and when you hear her coming close, 
 throw the towel, and there will be a wide, wide river. 
 
 And if Baba Yaga crosses that river and begins to catch up with you, 
 
 put your ear to the ground again, and when you hear her coming close, 
 
 throw your comb, and there will be a very thick forest-she will not be able to get through it." 
  </DonorFunctions>
  
 <StruggleVictory>
 The girl took the towel and the comb and ran. 
 
 The dogs wanted to tear her, but she threw them some bread and they let her pass. 
 
 The gates wanted to bang shut, but she poured some oil on their hinges and they let her pass. 
 
 The birch wanted to lash her eyes, 
 but she tied it with a ribbon and it let her pass. 
 
 Meanwhile the cat sat at the loom and wove; 
 
 he did not so much weave as tangle everything up. 
 Baba Yaga came to the window and asked: 
 "Are you weaving, little niece, are you weaving, my darling?" 
 
 "I am weaving, auntie, I am weaving, my dear," answered the cat in a rough voice. 
 
 Baba Yaga rushed into the hut, saw that the girl had gone, 
 and took to beating the cat and scolding him for not having scratched out the girl's eyes. 
 
 "I have served you so many years," said the cat, 
 "and you have not given me even a bone; but she gave me a piece of ham!"
 
 Baba Yaga flung herself on the dogs, the gate, the birch, and the maid, 
 and began to thrash and scold them all. 
 
 The dogs said to her: "We have served you so long, 
 and you have not even thrown us a burnt crust; but she gave us bread!" 
 
 The gate said: "I have served you so long, and you have not even poured water on my hinges; 
 but she poured oil!" 
 
 The birch said: "I have served you so long, 
 and you have not even tied me with a thread; but she tied me with a ribbon!" 
 
 The maid said: "I have served you so long, 
 and you have not given me even a rag; but she gave me a kerchief!" 
 
 Baba Yaga the Bony-legged jumped on her mortar, goaded it on with her pestle, 
 swept away her tracks with a broom, and flew in pursuit of the girl. 
 
 The girl put her ear to the ground and heard Baba Yaga coming quite close. 
 
 She threw her towel -and there was a wide, wide river. 
 
 Baba Yaga came to the river and gnashed her teeth with rage. 
 
 She returned home, took her oxen, and drove them to the river; 
 
 the oxen drank the river clean. Then she set out again in pursuit. 
 
 The girl put her ear to the ground and heard Baba Yaga coming close. 
 
 She threw her comb-and there grew up a deep and terrifying forest. 
 
 Baba Yaga began to gnaw it, but no matter how she tried she could not gnaw through it, 
 and she turned back.
 
 
 </StruggleVictory>
 
 <Return>
 Meanwhile the old man had come home and asked: "Where is my daughter?" 
 
 "She has gone to her aunt," said the stepmother. 
 
 After a while the girl also came home. 
 
 "Where have you been?" her father asked her. 
 
 "Ah, father," she said, "mother sent me to auntie for a needle and thread to sew me a shirt; 
 
 but the aunt was Baba Yaga and she wanted to eat me." 
 
 "How did you get away, my daughter?" The daughter told him how. 
 </Return>
 <PunishmentOfFalseHero>
 When the old man heard all this he grew angry at his wife and shot her to death;
 
 
 and then he and his daughter began to live and prosper. 
 </PunishmentOfFalseHero>
 <Epilogue>
 
 I was there and drank mead and beer; 
 
 it ran down my mustache, but it never got into my mouth. 
 </Epilogue>

</Move>
</Folktale>





 

<Folktale>

<!-- PG. 45
    alpha A/a? o F4 F3 connect M N W** 
    -->
<Move>
<Preparation>
A long time ago there lived a merchant and his wife; they had one child, a girl called Vasilisa. 

One day the mother placed a little doll in the child's hands, she said, 

"My child, I am dying. Take this doll as my blessing. 

Always keep it with you and never show it to anybody. 

If anything bad happens to you, give the doll food and ask her for guidance." 

Shortly afterwards the mother died.


The Merchant soon became lonely and decided to marry again. 

He married a widow he thought would be a good mother but both she 
and her two daughters were envious of Vasilisa's beauty. 
</Preparation>

<Villainy>
They gave her heavy outdoor work to do, 
so she would grow thin and her face turn ugly in the wind and the sun.
</Villainy>

<ConnectiveIncident>
Despite this, Vasilisa became more beautiful every day. 

For each day she gave her doll food and asked for advice. 

Having finished eating, the doll would help with the tasks and even bring Vasilisa herbs to prevent sunburn.


As the years passed, Vasilisa grew ever more beautiful as her stepmother's hatred of her intensified.
</ConnectiveIncident>

<Departure>
Then, whilst Vasilisa's father was away on business, 
the stepmother moved the family to the edge of a dense birch forest. 

This was not just any birch forest, for in this forest lived the terrifying witch, Baba-Yaga. 

A witch who ate people like others ate chicken.

Every day, the stepmother sent Vasilisa into the forest, but the girl always returned safe and sound with the 
guidance of her magic doll.
</Departure>

<DonorFunctions>
Then one night, the stepmother crept around the house and extinguished all the candles. 

As the last candle failed, she said in a loud voice.

"It's impossible to finish our work in the darkness. 

Somebody must go to Baba-Yaga and ask for a light."

"I'm not going," said the first stepdaughter, who was stitching lace. 

"I can see my needle."

"And I'm not going," said the second stepdaughter, who was knitting stockings, "I can see my needle."

So Vasilisa was thrown out into the dark forbidding forest. 

Despite her fear, she fed her magic doll and asked for its advice.


"Don't be afraid, Vasilisa," said the doll. 

"Go to Baba-Yaga and ask her to give you a light."

All that night, Vasilisa walked nervously through the forest holding the doll who guided her path. 

Then suddenly, she saw a horseman rushing by. 

His face and clothes were white and he was riding a white horse. 

As he passed the first light of dawn appeared across the sky. 

Then, another horseman came by. 

His face and clothes were red and he was riding a red horse. 

As he passed the sun began to rise. 

Vasilisa had never seen such strange men and she was very surprised.

She walked all day, until at last she came to Baba-Yaga's hut, 

which stood forbidding on its large chicken legs. 

A fence made of human bones surrounded the hut. 

It was crowned with human skulls. 

The gate had a sharp set of teeth that served as a lock. 

Vasilisa was terribly afraid.


Suddenly, another horseman galloped by. 

His face and clothes were black and he was riding a black horse. 

He rode through the gates and disappeared. 

As he passed, night descended.

As the sky darkened the eyes of the skulls began to glow. 

Their light illuminated the forest. 

Vasilisa trembled, she wanted to run but her legs would not move. 

Almost immediately she heard a hideous noise. 

The earth shook, the trees groaned and there was Baba-Yaga, riding in her mortar. 

She stopped and sniffed the air.

"I smell a human!" she cried. "Who is here?"

Vasilisa stepped forward, trembling with fear. 

She said, "I am, Vasilisa. My stepmother sent me to you to ask for a light."

"I know of her." 

Baba-Yaga replied. 

"Stay with me for a while. If you work well, I will give you light. 

If you do not, I will cook you and eat you."

Baba-Yaga commanded the gates to open and rode in. 

Vasilisa followed and the gates closed fast behind her.

As they entered the hut, Baba-Yaga ordered Vasilisa to bring her what was on the stove. 

There was enough food to feed ten men; 

then from the cupboard she collected kvas, mead, beer and wine. 

Baba-Yaga ate and drank everything. 

She left Vasilisa nothing but a crust of bread.

"I'm tired," Baba-Yaga said. 

"Tomorrow, Vasilisa, you must clean the yard, sweep the hut, cook the supper and wash the linen."

"Then," she added, 

"You must go to the corn bin and separate seed by seed the mildewed corn from the good corn, 
and mind that you remove all the black bits. 

If you don't complete these tasks I will eat you."

Soon Baba-Yaga started snoring, her long nose rattled against the roof of the hut. 

Vasilisa took her doll out of her pocket, gave it a crust of bread and said, 

"Please help me. 

Baba-Yaga has given me an impossible task to do and if I fail she will eat me."

The doll replied, 

"Don't be afraid, Vasilisa, eat your supper and go to bed. 

Mornings are wiser than evenings."

Although Vasilisa woke early the next morning, Baba-Yaga was already up. 

Vasilisa went to the corn bin and found the doll picking out the last black bits. 

The other tasks were also fulfilled. 

The doll said, "All you have to do now is prepare the supper and after that you can rest." 

Vasilisa thanked the doll and went to prepare supper. 

She cooked the food, laid the table and waited.


As the skulls' eyes began to shine, the trees groaned, the earth trembled, and there was Baba-Yaga.

"Have you done what I told you?" she asked Vasilisa.

"See for yourself," replied the girl.

Baba-Yaga was very upset, for she wanted to eat the girl but the tasks were all completed. 

Hiding her anger, she said, "Very good," and then cried loudly, 

"My faithful servants grind the wheat!"

From nowhere three pairs of hands appeared. 

They took the wheat and vanished.

Baba-Yaga ate the supper and said to Vasilisa, 

"Tomorrow you must do the same tasks 
and then you must go to the store room 
and sort out the dirt from the poppy seeds."


The next morning Baba-Yaga again rode off in her mortar. 

Vasilisa, with the help of her doll, finished the tasks. 

In the evening the old woman came back and checked everything over. 

Three pairs of hands appeared. 

They took the bin of poppy seeds and vanished.

Baba-Yaga sat down to eat.
"Why," she said, "do you sit there so quiet and still?"
"I'm afraid to speak," said Vasilisa, 

"would you mind if I asked you some questions?"
"Ask if you want," said Baba-Yaga, 
"but remember that not every question has a good answer."


Vasilisa hesitated, "It's just that on my way here I saw a white horseman. Who was he?"

"That was my Bright Day," answered Baba-Yaga.
Vasilisa continued, "Then I saw a red horseman. Who was he?"
"That was my Red Sun," answered Baba-Yaga.
"And then a black horseman overtook me whilst I was standing outside your gate. Who was he?"
"That was my Black Midnight," answered Baba-Yaga. 

"These horsemen are my faithful servants. 
Have you further questions?"

Vasilisa remembered the three pairs of hands but remained quiet.
"Now I have a question for you. 
How have you managed to carry out all the work so quickly?"
Vasilisa replied, "My mother's blessing helped me."
"I knew it," said Baba-Yaga. 
"You'd better be gone. 
I will not have people with blessings in my home."
With that, the old woman pushed Vasilisa out of the hut and through the gate.

Then she took one of the skulls, stuck it on the end of a stick and gave it to the girl, saying: 

"Here's a light for your stepmother and her daughters. 

That's what you came here for, isn't it?"


She walked all day and by the evening she reached her home. 

As she approached the gates she was about to throw away the skull, 

but suddenly she heard a muffled voice say: 

"You must keep me, your stepmother and her daughters have need of me."

The girl carried the skull into the house. 

As she entered, the skull fixed its eyes on the stepmother and her two daughters. 

Its eyes burnt them like fire. 

They tried to hide, but the piercing eyes followed them and never let them out of their sight. 

By morning nothing was left of the three women except three heaps of ash on the floor.

Vasilisa was unharmed.


She buried the skull in the garden and went to find shelter in the nearest town. 

Here she lodged with an old woman.

One day the old woman gave Vasilisa some flax. 

With it Vasilisa spun the most beautiful thread, so fine it was like hair. 

Then she weaved the thread into the most exquisite cloth. 

It was brilliant white, soft and so beautiful. 

Vasilisa gave it to the old woman and said: 

"Grandmother, you have been so kind to me, sell this cloth and keep the money."

The old woman looked at it and said, 

"My child, this is too fine to sell. 

I am going to take it to the Tsar."

So she brought it to the Tsar as a gift. 

The Tsar thanked the old woman and gave her many presents before sending her home.


Impressed with the beautiful cloth, the Tsar tried to find someone who could make shirts from it. 

However all the tailors declined the work, as the cloth was too fine for them to handle. 

In the end the Tsar called the old woman and said, "You must also know how to sew the cloth as you made it."

The old woman replied, "No your Majesty. 

It was not my work. 

It was done by a girl I took in."


So the Tsar asked the old woman to see if Vasilisa would make the garments. 

Vasilisa made the shirts and the old woman took them to the Tsar.


As she waited for the old woman to return, one of the Tsar's servants entered. 

He said loudly, 

"His Majesty wishes to see the needlewoman who has made his wonderful clothes." 

So Vasilisa went to the palace.

</DonorFunctions>
<Wedding>
Vasilisa and the Tsar were captivated by each other and eventually they married.


When Vasilisa's father returned, they invited both him and the old woman to come and live at the palace. 

Also at the palace was the little doll, for Vasilisa carried it around in her pocket until the day she died.
</Wedding>
</Move>
</Folktale>





<!--
  A_1 B C depart D1_1 E1_1 F1  d2_7 E2_7 F2_9 G_4      K_1 return 
    -->
<Folktale>
<Move>
<Preparation>
Once upon a time a man and a woman lived with their daughter and small son.
"Dearest daughter," said the mother, "we are going to work. Look after your brother! 
Don't go out of the yard, be a good girl, and we'll buy you a handkerchief."
The father and mother went off to work, and the daughter soon enough forgot what they had told her. 
She put her little brother on the grass under a window and ran into the yard, 
where she played and got completely carried away having fun.
</Preparation>
<Villainy>
In swooped the swan-geese, snatched up the little boy, and flew away with him.

When the girl came back inside, her brother was missing! "Oh no!" she cried. 
She dashed here and there, but there was no sign of him. 
She called for him, cried, and wailed how angry mother and father would be, 
but her brother did not answer.
</Villainy>
<ConsentToCounteraction>
Then she ran out to the edge of the fields, and just managed to catch sight 
of the swan-geese rushing into the distance and disappearing into the forest. 

She suspected that they were taking her brother off with them. 
Swan-geese had long held a bad reputation for being naughty and carrying away little children.
</ConsentToCounteraction>
<Departure>
The girl rushed to catch up with them. She ran and ran, until she saw an oven.
</Departure>
<DonorFunctions>
"Little oven, little oven, tell me, where did the swan-geese fly to?"
"Eat up some of my rye buns, and I will tell you."
"I'm not going to eat your rye buns! I don't even eat the wheat ones we have at home."
The oven did not tell her. The girl ran further, until she came to an apple tree.
"Apple tree, apple tree, tell me, where did the swan-geese fly to?"
"Eat some of my wild apples, and I will tell you."
"I'm not going to eat your wild apples! I don't even eat the apples from our garden at home."
The apple tree did not tell her. So the girl ran further, 
until she came to a river of milk flowing in banks of pudding.
"River of milk, banks of pudding, where did the swan-geese fly to?"
"Eat up some of my humble pudding with milk, and I will tell you."
"I'm not going to eat your simple pudding with milk! 
I don't even eat the pudding we have at home."
</DonorFunctions>
<Transference>
For a long time she ran through clearings and through forest. 
The day drew toward evening, and there was nothing to do--she had to go home. 
But when she turned around, she suddenly saw a little cabin with one little window.
In the cabin was the old witch Baba Yaga, spinning flax. 
And on a little bench sat her brother, playing with a silver apple.
The girl ran into the cabin.
</Transference>
<TaskSolution>
"Hello, old woman!"
"Hello, maiden. Why have you burst into my house like this?"
"I came through the forest and through the swamp, and my dress is torn to shreds. 
I would like to warm up a little here."
"Sit over there and spin some flax."
Baba Yaga gave her a spindle and left her alone. 
The girl was spinning away, when suddenly a mouse darted out from under the stove and said to her, 
"Maiden, maiden, give me a bit of porridge and I will tell you things you need to know."
</TaskSolution>
<DonorFunctions>
The girl gave her a bit of porridge, and the mouse told her, 
"Baba Yaga has gone to the bath house to stoke the fire. 
She is going to steam you, put you in the oven, roast you, eat you up, 
and then ride away on two of your bones."
The girl sat in a state of shock, crying, but the mouse spoke to her again. 
"Don't wait! Pick up your brother, run, and I will spin the flax in your place."
</DonorFunctions>

<LiquidationOfLack>
The girl snatched up her brother and set out running. </LiquidationOfLack>
<TaskSolution>
After she was gone, Baba Yaga went up to the window and asked, "Maiden, are you spinning?"
"I'm spinning, old woman," answered the mouse.
The old witch, satisfied, went back to the bath house. 
</TaskSolution>
<PursuitRescue>
When she had gotten the fire hot enough, she went to get the girl. 
But in the cabin there was nobody. 
She cried, "Swan-geese! After them! 
The sister has stolen her brother and run away!"
The girl, her brother in her arms, ran up to the river of milk. 
She saw that the swan-geese were flying after her.
"Mother river, hide me!"
"Eat up some of my simple pudding."
The girl ate and thanked the river, and the river sheltered her under its banks of pudding. 
The swan-geese did not see her, and flew past.
The girl set out running again, her brother in her arms.
But the swan-geese came back, and flew in her direction, there--there! 
They saw them! What to do? Trouble! But there stood the apple tree.
"Mother apple tree, hide me!"
"Eat some of my wild apples."
The girl quickly ate one and thanked the tree, and the tree hid her with its branches, 
sheltered her with its leaves.
The swan-geese didn't see them, and flew past.
The girl ran again. She ran and ran, until she was almost exhausted. 
The swan-geese saw her again, and began to cackle. 
They flew in on her, and beat their wings 
as if at any moment they would snatch her brother from her arms.
The girl ran up to the oven:
"Mother oven, hide me!"
"Eat some of my rye buns."

The girl quickly popped a bun into her mouth and settled herself and her brother into the oven.

The swan-geese flew and flew, called and called, 
but finally they gave up and flew away, back to the old woman.
</PursuitRescue>
<Return>
The girl thanked the oven and, together with her brother, ran all the way home.
And just after they got there, their father and mother returned.
</Return>
</Move>
</Folktale>





 
 <!-- 
   A_1 B_4 C depart           H_1  I_1 K_4 return        W
     -->
<Folktale>
<Move>
<Preparation>
 
 A dragon appeared near Kiev; 
 
 he took heavy tribute from the people-a lovely maiden from every house, whom he then devoured. 
 
 Finally, it was the fate of the tsar's daughter to go to the dragon. 
 </Preparation>
 <Villainy>
 He seized her and dragged her to his lair but did not devour her, because she was a beauty. 
 
 Instead, he took her to wife.
 
 Whenever he went out, he boarded up his house to prevent the princess from escaping. 
 </Villainy>
 
 <ConnectiveIncident>
 The princess had a little dog that had followed her to the dragon's lair. 
 
 The princess often wrote to her father and mother. 
 
 She would attach her letter to the dog's neck, 
   and the dog would take it to them and even bring back the answer. 
 
 One day the tsar and tsarina wrote to their daughter, 
   asking her to find out who in this world was stronger than the dragon. 
   
   The princess became kindlier toward the dragon and began to question him. 
   
   For a long time he did not answer, 
   but one day he said  inadvertently that a tanner in the city of Kiev was stronger than he.
   
 When the princess heard this, 
 she wrote her father to find Nikita the Tanner in Kiev 
 and to send him to deliver her from captivity. 
 </ConnectiveIncident>
 <ConsentToCounteraction>
 Upon receiving this letter, the tsar went in person 
 
 to beg Nikita the Tanner to free his land from the wicked dragon and rescue the princess. 
 
 At that moment Nikita was currying hides and held twelve hides in his hands; 
 
 when he saw that the tsar in person had come to see him, 
 he began to tremble with fear, 
 his hands shook, and he tore the twelve hides. 
 
 But no matter how much the tsar 
 and tsarina entreated him, 
 he refused to go forth against the dragon. 
 
 So they gathered together five thousand little 
 children and sent them to implore him, 
 hoping that their tears would move him to pity. 
 
 The little children came to Nikita and begged him with tears to go fight the dragon. 
 
 Nikita himself began to shed tears when he saw theirs. 
 
 He took twelve thousand pounds of hemp, tarred it with pitch, 
 and wound it around himself so that the dragon could not devour him, 
 then went forth to give him battle. 
 </ConsentToCounteraction>
 <Departure>
 Nikita came to the dragon's lair but the dragon locked himself in. 
 </Departure>
 
 <StruggleVictory>
 "Better come out into the open field," said 
 Nikita, "or I will destroy your lair together with you!" And he began to break down the door. The dragon, seeing 
 that he could not avoid trouble, went out to fight in the open field. Nikita fought him for a long time or a 
 short time; in any event, he defeated him. Then the dragon began to implore Nikita: "Do not put me to death, 
 Nikita the Tanner; no one in the world is stronger than you and I. Let us divide all the earth, all the world, 
 into equal parts; you shall live in one half, I in the other." "Very well," said Nikita, "let us draw a boundary 
 line." He made a plow that weighed twelve thousand pounds, harnessed the dragon to it, and the dragon began to 
 plow a boundary from Kiev; he plowed a furrow from Kiev to the Caspian Sea. "Now," said the dragon, "we have 
 divided the whole earth." "We have divided the earth," said Nikita, "now let us divide the sea; else you will 
 say that your water has been taken." The dragon crawled to the middle of the sea; Nikita killed him and drowned 
 him in the sea. 
 </StruggleVictory>
 <Return>
 That furrow can be seen to this very day; it is fourteen feet high. Around it the fields are plowed, but the 
 furrow is intact; and those who do not know what it is, call it the rampart. Nikita, having done his heroic 
 deed, would not accept any reward, but returned to currying hides. 
 </Return>
</Move>
</Folktale>





<!-- 
  A_1 B_3 C depart D1_2 E1_2 F1_2 G_2 D2_1 E2_1 F2_2 G_5 o L HMPr J INRs K return PrH RsI L Q Ex T U W X MOVE
   a_1 B_4 C depart D1_4 E1_4 F1_6 G_5     o L HMPr J INRs K return PrH RsI L Q Ex T U W X MOVE
   A_7  C depart    G_1     o L HMPr J INRs K return PrH RsI L Q Ex T U W X 
    -->
<Folktale>
<Move>
<Preparation>
 Once there was a king who had an only son. 
 
 When the prince was small, his nurses and governesses sang lullabies to him. 
 
 "Prince Ivan, when you grow up, you will find your bride," they would sing. 
 </Preparation>
 <Lack>
 "Beyond thrice nine lands, in the thrice tenth kingdom, 
 Vasilisa Kirbitievna sits in a tower, and her marrow flows from bone to bone." 
 </Lack>
 <Departure>
 When the prince had passed his fifteenth year, he began to ask the king's leave to set out in search of his bride. 
 
 "Whither will you go?"
 the father asked. 
 
 "You are still too young." "No, father, when I was little, 
 my nurses and governesses sang lullabies to me and told me where my bride lives; 
 and now I wish to go and find her." 
 
 The father gave the prince his blessing and sent word to all the kingdoms that his son, Prince Ivan,
 was setting out to find his bride. 
 </Departure>
 
<DonorFunctions>
 One day the prince came to a certain town, put up his horse to 
 be cared for, and went to walk in the streets. He came to 
 the square and saw that a man was being flogged with a whip. 
 "Why do you whip him?" he asked. "Because he borrowed ten 
 thousand rubles from a prominent merchant," they told him, 
 "and did not pay them back at the agreed time. As for the 
 man who redeems him, his wife will be carried off by Koshchey 
 the Deathless." The prince thought and thought and went away. 
 He walked through the town, then came to the square again, and 
 saw that the man was still being flogged; Prince Ivan took pity 
 on him and decided to redeem him. Since I have no wife, he 
 thought, no one can be taken from me. He paid the ten thousand 
 rubles and went home. Suddenly the man whom he had redeemed ran 
 after him, crying: "Thank you, Prince Ivan! If you had not 
 redeemed me, you would never have won your bride. But now I will 
 help you. Buy me a horse and a saddle at once." The prince bought
 him a horse and saddle and asked: "What is your name?" "My name is 
 Bulat the Brave," the man said. 
 They mounted their horses and set out. 
 </DonorFunctions>
 
 <TaskSolution>
 As soon as they arrived in the thrice tenth kingdom, Bulat said: 
 
 "Well, Prince Ivan, order chickens, ducks, and geese to be bought and roasted, 
 so that there will be plenty of everything. 
 
 And I will get your bride. 
 
 But mind you: 
 
 every time I come to you, cut off the right wing of a fowl and serve it to me on a plate." 
 
 Bulat the Brave went straight to the lofty tower where Vasilisa Kirbitievna was sitting, gently 
 threw a stone, and broke the gilded top of the tower. 
 
 He ran to Prince Ivan and said: 
 
 "Why are you sleeping? Give me a chicken." 
 
 The prince cut off the right wing of a chicken and handed it to him on a plate. 
 
 Bulat took the plate, ran to the tower, and cried: 
 
"Good day, Vasilisa Kirbitievna! Prince Ivan sends you his 
greetings and has asked me to give you this chicken." The maiden 
was frightened and sat in silence. But he answered himself in 
her stead: "Good day, Bulat the Brave! Is Prince Ivan well? 
Thank God, he is well. And why do you stand like that, Bulat the 
Brave? Take the key, open the cupboard, drink a glass of vodka, 
and God speed you. 
 
Then Bulat ran to Prince Ivan. 
 
"Why are you sitting?" he said. 
"Give me a duck." The prince cut off the right wing of a duck and 
handed it to him on a plate. Bulat took the plate and carried it 
to the tower. "Good day, Vasilisa Kirbitievna! Prince Ivan sends 
you his greetings and has asked me to give you this duck." She
sat in silence, and he answered himself in her stead: "Good day,
Bulat the Brave! Is the prince well? Thank God, he is well. And 
why do you stand like that, Bulat the Brave? Take the key, open
the cupboard, drink a glass of vodka, and God speed you." Then 
Bulat ran home and again said to Prince Ivan: "Why are you 
sitting? Give me a goose." 


The prince cut off the right wing of a goose and handed it to him on a plate. 

Bulat the Brave took it to the tower. 

"Good day, Vasilisa Kirbitievna! Prince Ivan sends his greetings and has asked me to give you this goose."

Vasilisa Kirbitievna straightway took a key, opened a cupboard, and gave him a glass of vodka. 

</TaskSolution>
<Wedding>
Bulat did not take the glass, but seized the maiden by her right hand, drew her out of the tower,
and seated her on Prince Ivan's horse, and the good youths gall.
</Wedding>
</Move>
</Folktale>





<!-- 
Dpre_6 Epre_6 Fpre_1 A_11 H_1 I_1 K_8 W X MOVE
A_1 B_3 C depart H_1 I_1 K_4 W X
   -->
<Folktale>
<Move>
<Preparation>
 In A certain kingdom in a certain land there lived a king who had three sons. 
 
 One day they said to him: 
 
 "Father, our gracious sovereign, give us your blessing; 
 
 we wish to go hunting." 
 
 The father gave them his blessing and they set out in different directions. 
 </Preparation>
 <Departure>
 The youngest son rode and rode and lost his way; 
 </Departure>
 <DonorFunctions>
 he came to a clearing, and there lay a dead horse,
 around which were gathered beasts of many kinds, birds, and reptiles. 
 A falcon rose, flew up to the prince, perched on his shoulder, and said: 
 "Prince Ivan, divide that horse among us; 
 it has lain here for thirty years, 
 and we have been quarreling ever since, 
 unable to find a way of sharing it." 
 
 The prince climbed down from his good steed and divided the carcass: 
 he gave the bones to the beasts, 
 the flesh to the birds, 
 the skin to the reptiles, 
 and the head to the ants. 
 
 "Thank you, Prince Ivan," 
 
 said the falcon. 
 
 "For your kindness you shall be able to turn into a bright falcon or an ant whenever you wish." 
 </DonorFunctions>
 
 
 
 <Transfiguration>
 Prince Ivan struck the damp earth, 
 turned into a bright falcon, 
 soared up into the air, 
 and flew to the thrice tenth kingdom. 
 </Transfiguration>
 <Villainy>
 More than half of that kingdom had been swallowed into a crystal mountain. 
 </Villainy>
 
 <ConsentToCounteraction>
 The prince flew straight into the royal palace, 
 turned into a goodly youth, and asked the palace guards: 
 
 "Will your king take me into his service?" 
 "Why should he not take such a goodly youth?" they answered. 
 
 Thus he entered the service of that king and lived in his palace for one week, 
 then a second, 
 then a third. 
 </ConsentToCounteraction>
 <Departure>
 The king's daughter asked her father: 
 "Father, my sovereign, 
 give me leave to take a ride with Prince Ivan to the crystal mountain." 
 
 The king gave her leave. 
 
 They mounted good steeds and set out. 
 </Departure>
 </Move>
 <Move>
 <Villainy>
 When they approached the crystal mountain, 
 a golden goat jumped suddenly out from nowhere. 
 The prince chased it; 
 
 he galloped and galloped, 
 but could not catch the goat, 
 and when he returned the princess had vanished. 
 
 What was he to do? 
 
 How could he dare to appear before the king? 
 </Villainy> <!--Lack -->
 <ConsentToCounterAction>
 He disguised himself as a very old man, 
 so that he would be unrecognizable, 
 came to the palace, 
 and said to the king: 
 
 "Your Majesty, 
 hire me as your herdsman." 
 
 "Very well," 
 said the king, 
 "be my herdsman. 
 
 When the three-headed dragon comes to your herd, 
 give him three cows; 
 
 when the six-headed dragon comes, 
 give him six cows; 
 
 and when the twelve-headed dragon comes, 
 count off twelve cows." 
 </ConsentToCounterAction>
 
  <StruggleVictory>
 Prince Ivan drove his herd over mountains and valleys. 
 Suddenly the three-headed dragon came flying from a lake and said: 
 
 "Ah, Prince Ivan, what kind of work are you engaged in? 
 A goodly youth like you should be vying in combat, 
 not tending cattle. 
 Well, let me have three cows!" 
 
 "Won't that be too much?" asked the prince. 
 
 "I myself eat only one duck a day, 
 and you want three cows. 
 But you won't get any!" 
 
 The dragon flew into a rage, 
 and instead of three cows, 
 seized six. 
 
 Prince Ivan straightway turned into a bright falcon, 
 cut off all the three heads of the dragon, 
 and drove the cattle home. 
 
 "Well, grandfather," 
 asked the king, 
 "has the three-headed dragon come? 
 Did you give him three cows?" 
 "No, Your Majesty," 
 replied Prince Ivan, 
 "I did not give him any." 
  </StruggleVictory>
 
 <StruggleVictory>
 Next day the prince drove his herd over mountains and valleys, 
 and the six-headed dragon came from the lake and demanded six cows. 
 "Ah, you gluttonous monster," 
 said the prince, 
 "I myself eat only one duck a day, 
 and see what you demand! I won't give you any!" 
 The dragon flew into a rage and instead of six, seized twelve cows; 
 but the prince turned into a bright falcon, 
 fell upon the dragon, and cut off his six heads. 
 
 He drove the herd,home and the king asked him: 
 "Well, grandfather, has the six-headed dragon come? 
 Has my herd grown much smaller?" 
 "Come he did, but he took nothing," 
 answered the prince. 
 </StruggleVictory>
 
 <StruggleVictory>
 Late at night Prince Ivan turned into an ant 
  and crawled into the crystal mountain through a little crack. 
 Lo and behold, the princess was in the crystal mountain. 
 "Good evening!" said Prince Ivan. 
 "How did you get here?" 
 "The twelve-headed dragon carried me off," said the princess. 
 "He lives in father's lake and has a coffer in his side. 
 In this coffer is a hare, 
 in this hare is a duck, 
 in this duck is an egg, 
 and in this egg is a seed. 
 
 If you slay the dragon and get that seed, 
 it will be possible to destroy the crystal mountain and rescue me." 
 
 Prince Ivan crawled out of the mountain, 
 turned again into a herdsman, 
 and drove his herd. 
</StruggleVictory>
 <StruggleVictory> 
 Suddenly the twelve-headed dragon flew up to him and said: 
 "Ah, Prince Ivan, 
 you are not doing what you should; 
 a goodly youth like you should be vying in combat, 
 not tending a herd. Well, count off twelve cows for me!" 
 "That will be too much for you!" said the prince. 
 "I myself eat only one duck a day, and see what you demand!" 
 They began to fight, and after a long struggle or a short struggle, 
 Prince Ivan defeated the twelve-headed dragon, 
 slashed open his trunk, and found the coffer in his right side. 
 In the coffer he found a hare, 
 in the hare a duck, 
 in the duck an egg, 
 in the egg a seed. 
 He took the seed, 
 set it alight, 
 and brought it to the crystal mountain, 
 which soon melted away. 
</StruggleVictory>
 <Wedding>
 Prince Ivan led the princess to her father, 
 who was overjoyed and said to the prince: 
 "Be my son-in-law!" 
 The wedding was held at once. 
 </Wedding>
 <Epilogue>
 I was at that wedding too. I drank beer and mead; they flowed down my beard but did not go into my mouth. 
 </Epilogue>
 
</Move>
</Folktale>






<!-- 
   A_5 B_1 C depart              K_7 return          MOVE
   a_6  C depart D1_1 E1_1 F1_5 G_5   F2_1 G_2     I_5  return          MOVE 
   A_1  C depart d1_7 E1_7 F1_9 G_1     o L M  N K     Q Ex  U W
    -->
<Folktale>
<Move>


<Preparation>Once upon a time there lived a king and queen. They had three sons, two of them with their wits about them, but 
the third a simpleton. Now the King had a deer-park in which were quantities of wild animals of different kinds. 
</Preparation>
<Villainy>
Into that park there used to come a huge beastNorka was its nameand do fearful mischief, devouring some of the 
animals every night.
</Villainy>

<ConsentToCounterAction>
The King did all he could, but he was unable to destroy it. So at last he called his sons 
together and said: Whoever will destroy the Norka, to him will I give the half of my kingdom.
</ConsentToCounterAction>
<AlienForms>
Well, the eldest son undertook the task. As soon as it was night, he took his weapons and set out. 


But before he reached the park, he went into a tavern, and there he spent the whole night in revelry.

When he came to his senses it was too late; the day had already dawned. 


He felt himself disgraced in the eyes of his father, but there was no help for it. 
</AlienForms>
<AlienForms>
The next day the second son went, and did just the same. 

Their father scolded them both soundly, and there was an end of it.
</AlienForms>

<Departure>
Well, on the third day the youngest son undertook the task. 

They all laughed him to scorn, because he was so stupid, feeling sure he wouldnt do anything. 

But he took his arms, and went straight into the park, 
and sat down on the grass in such a position that, the moment he went asleep, his weapons would prick him, 
and he would awake.
</Departure>


<StruggleVictory>

Presently the midnight hour sounded. 

The earth began to shake, and the Norka came rushing up, and burst right through the fence into the park, 
so huge was it. 

The Prince pulled himself together, leapt to his feet, crossed himself, and went straight at the beast. 

It fled back, and the Prince ran after it. 

But he soon saw that he couldnt catch it on foot, so he hastened to the stable, 
laid his hands on the best horse there, and set off in pursuit. 

Presently he came up with the beast, and they began a fight. 

They fought and fought; 

the Prince gave the beast three wounds. 

At last they were both utterly exhausted, so they lay down to take a short rest. 





But the moment the Prince closed his eyes, up jumped the Beast and took to flight. 

The Princes horse awoke him; up he jumped in a moment, and set off again in pursuit, caught up the Beast, 
and again began fighting with it. 



Again the Prince gave the Beast three wounds, and then he and the Beast lay down again to rest. 

Thereupon away fled the Beast as before. 

The Prince caught it up, and again gave it three wounds. 

But all of a sudden, just as the Prince began chasing it for the fourth time, 
the Beast fled to a great white stone, tilted it up, and escaped into the other 
world, crying out to the Prince: 

Then only will you overcome me, when you enter here.

</StruggleVictory>


<Return>

The Prince went home, told his father all that had happened, 
and asked him to have a leather rope plaited, long enough to reach to the other world. 
</Return>

</Move>
<Move>
<Departure>
His father ordered this to be done. When the rope was made, the Prince called for his brothers, 
and he and they, having taken servants with them, 
and everything that was needed for a whole year, 
set out for the place where the Beast had disappeared under the stone. 

</Departure>

<TaskSolution>
When they got there, they built a palace on the spot, 
and lived in it for some time. But when everything was ready, 
the youngest brother said to the others: 

Now, brothers, who is going to lift this stone?




Neither of them could so much as stir it, but as soon as he touched it, 
away it flew to a distance, though it was ever so bigbig as a hill. 


And when he had flung the stone aside, he spoke a second time to his brothers, saying:

Who is going into the other world, to overcome the Norka?

Neither of them offered to do so. 

Then he laughed at them for being such cowards, and said:

Well, brothers, farewell! Lower me into the other world, and dont go away from here, 
but as soon as the cord is jerked, pull it up.

His brothers lowered him accordingly, 
and when he had  reached the other world, underneath the earth, he went on his way. 


</TaskSolution>

<Filler>

He walked and walked. 

Presently he espied a horse with rich trappings, and it said to him:

Hail, Prince Ivan! Long have I awaited thee!

He mounted the horse and rode onrode and rode, until he saw standing before him, a palace made of copper. 

He entered the courtyard, tied up his horse, and went indoors. 

In one of the rooms a dinner was laid out. 

He sat down and dined, and then went into a bedroom. 

There he found a bed, on which he lay down to rest.



Presently there came in a lady, more beautiful than can be imagined anywhere but in a skazka, who said:

Thou who art in my house, name thyself! 




If thou art an old man, thou shall be my father; if a middle-aged man, my brother; 

but if a young man, thou shalt be my husband dear. 

And if thou art a woman, and an old one, thou shalt be my grandmother; 

if middle-aged, my mother; 

and if a girl, thou shalt be my own sister.



Thereupon he came forth. And when she saw him, she was delighted with him, and said:

Wherefore, O Prince Ivanmy husband dear shalt thou be!wherefore hast thou come hither?



Then he told her all that had happened, and she said:

That beast which thou wishest to overcome is my brother. 

He is staying just now with my second sister, who lives not far from here in a silver palace. 

I bound up three of the wounds which thou didst give him.






Well, after this they drank, and enjoyed themselves, and held sweet converse together, 
and then the prince took leave of her, and went on to the second sister, the one who lived in the silver palace, 
and with her also he stayed awhile. 

She told him that her brother Norka was then at her youngest sisters. 

So he went on to the youngest sister, who lived in a golden palace. 

She told him that her brother was at that time asleep on the blue sea, and she gave him a sword of steel 
and a draught of the Water of Strength, 
and she told him to cut off her brothers head at a single stroke. 

And when he had heard these things, he went his way.

And when the Prince came to the blue sea, he lookedthere slept Norka on a stone in the middle of the sea; 

and when it snored, the water was agitated for seven versts around. 

The Prince crossed himself, went up to it and smote it on the head with his sword. 

The head jumped off, saying the while, Well, Im done for now! and rolled far away into the sea.





After killing the Beast, the Prince went back again, picking up all the three sisters by the way, 
with the intention of taking them out into the upper world: 

for they all loved him and would not be separated from him. 

Each of them turned her palace into an eggfor they were all enchantresses 
 and they taught him how to turn the eggs into palaces, 
and back again, and they handed over the eggs to him. 

And then they all went to the place from which they had to be hoisted into the upper world. 

And when they came to where the rope was, the Prince took hold of it and made the maidens fast to it. 

Then he jerked away at the rope, and his brothers began to haul it up. 
And when they had hauled it up, and had set eyes on the wondrous maidens, they went aside and said:

Lets lower the rope, pull our brother part of the way up, and then cut the rope. 
Perhaps hell be killed; but then if he isnt, hell never give us these beauties as wives.

So when they had agreed on this, they lowered the rope. But their brother was no fool; 
he guessed what they were at, so he fastened the rope to a stone, and then gave it a pull. 

His brothers hoisted the stone to a great height, and then cut the rope. 
Down fell the stone and broke in pieces; the Prince poured forth tears and went away. 

Well, he walked and walked. 
Presently a storm arose; the lightning flashed, the thunder roared, the rain fell in torrents. 

He went up to a tree in order to take shelter under it, 
and on that tree he saw some young birds which were being thoroughly drenched. 

So he took off his coat and covered them over with it, and he himself sat down under the tree. 

Presently there came flying a birdsuch a big one, that the light was blotted out by it. 

It had been dark there before, but now it became darker still. 

Now this was the mother of those small birds which the Prince had covered up. 

And when the bird had come flying up, she perceived that her little ones were covered over, and she said, 
Who has wrapped up my nestlings? and presently, seeing the Prince, she added: 

Didst thou do that? Thanks! In return, ask of me any thing thou desirest. 

I will do anything for thee.

Then carry me into the other world, he replied.

Make me a large zasyek[89] with a partition in the middle, she said; 

catch all sorts of game, and put them into one half of it, 
and into the other half pour water; so that there may be meat and drink for me.

All this the Prince did.
Then the birdhaving taken the zasyek on her back, with the Prince sitting in the middle of it 
 began to fly. 

And after flying some distance she brought him to his journeys end, took leave of him, and flew away back. 

But he went to the house of a certain tailor, and engaged himself as his servant. 

So much the worse for wear was he, so thoroughly had he altered in appearance, 
that nobody would have suspected him of being a Prince.

Having entered into the service of this master, the Prince began to ask what was going on in that country. 
And his master replied: Our two princesfor the third one has disappearedhave brought away brides 
from the other world, and want to marry them, but those brides refuse. 
For they insist on having all their wedding-clothes made for them first, exactly like those 
which they used to have in the other world, and that without being measured for them. 

The King has called all the workmen together, but not one of them will undertake to do it.




The Prince, having heard all this, said, Go to the King, master, and tell him that you will provide everything 
thats in your line.

However can I undertake to make clothes of that sort; I work for quite common folks, says his master.

Go along, master! I will answer for everything, says the Prince.

So the tailor went. The King was delighted that at least one good workman had been found, 
and gave him as much money as ever he wanted. 
When the tailor had settled everything, he went home. And the Prince said to him:

Now then, pray to God, and lie down to sleep; to-morrow all will be ready. And the tailor followed his lads 
advice, and went to bed.

Midnight sounded. 
The Prince arose, went out of the city into the fields, 
took out of his pocket the eggs which the maidens had given him, 
and, as they had taught him, turned them into three palaces. 

Into each of these he entered, took the maidens robes, went out again, 
turned the palaces back into eggs, and went home. 
And when he got there he hung up the robes on the wall, and lay down to sleep.




Early in the morning his master awoke, and behold! 
there hung such robes as he had never seen before, all shining with gold and silver and precious stones. 
He was delighted, and he seized them and carried them off to the King. 
When the princesses saw that the clothes were those which had been theirs in the other world, 
they guessed that Prince Ivan was in this world, 
so they exchanged glances with each other, but they held their peace. 
And the master, having handed over the clothes, went home, but he no longer found his dear journeyman there. 




For the Prince had gone to a shoemakers, and him too he sent to work for the King; 
and in the same way he went the round of all the artificers, 
and they all proffered him thanks, 
inasmuch as through him they were enriched by the King.





By the time the princely workman had gone the round of all the artificers, 
the princesses had received what they had asked for; 

all their clothes were just like what they had been in the other world. 

Then they wept bitterly 
because the Prince had not come, and it was impossible for them to hold out any longer, 
it was necessary that they should be married. But when they were ready for the wedding, 
the youngest bride said to the King:

 Allow me, my father, to go and give alms to the beggars.

He gave her leave, and she went and began bestowing alms upon them, and examining them closely. 



And when she had come to one of them, and was going to give him some money,
she caught sight of the ring which she had given to the Prince in the other world, 
and her sisters rings toofor it really was he. 

So she seized him by the hand, and brought him into the hall, and said to the King:

Here is he who brought us out of the other world. His brothers forbade us to say that he was alive, threatening 
to slay us if we did.
</Filler>

<PunishmentOfFalseHero>
Then the King was wroth with those sons, and punished them as he thought best. </PunishmentOfFalseHero>
<Wedding>
And afterwards three weddings were celebrated.

</Wedding>
</Move>
</Folktale>





</Corpus>
